Guide to the Josiah William Bailey Papers, 1833-1967, bulk 1900-1946 RL.00065
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Legal Materials Series, ca. 1900-1940
  - Case Files Subseries
    - Jones, Sallie Bailey (ca. 1922) Financial matters; Raleigh Banking and Loan. (Box 48)
    - Jones, William Bailey (ca. 1919-1929) Misc. legal matters. (Box 48)
    - Jones and Bailey (ca. 1916-1929). Financial information on accounts of Wesley N. Jones and Josiah W. Bailey. (Box 48)
    - Ku Klux Klan (ca. 1922-1925). (Box 48)
      This case involves the trial of W. V. Guerard, formerly King Kleagle of the Ku Klux Klan, for embezzlement of Klan funds. Bailey defended Guerard and perceived the case as a means to publicize the Klan as a corporation engaged in unlawful business (see letter of Dec. 18, 1922, to Harry Dougherty). Guerard later sued for slander and libel. This file is arranged in chronological order from 1922 through 1925 and includes printed Klan and records of expenses for material on the Klan propagation in N. C., as well as correspondence indicating Bailey's political interest in exposing the Klan.
    - Leigh, Benjamin W. (ca. 1925-1926) Estate. (Box 48)
    - Leitch, T. G. Relates to motion picture copyright infringement by North Carolina theater operators. (Box 49)
    - Lewis, Mrs. Clara B. (ca. 1922-1931). Assorted personal affairs. Bailey borrowed money from her and was a personal friend of Mr. and Mrs. Lewis. (Box 49)
    - Murray Company (ca. 1925). Pertains to a claim from Red Springs Cotton Mill. (Box 49)
    - Mutual Publishing Company (ca. 1911-1914). (Box 49)
    - Nash v. Royster (ca. 1925). Bailey defended Nash in a personal injury suit against Dr. A. H. Royster. (Box 49)
    - Nash v. Royster continued (Box 50)
    - Negro Fair (1925). (Box 50)
      Bailey sought a restraining order against the Ringling Brothers Circus which planned to hold its circus at the same time as a Negro Fair sponsored by the N. C. Industrial Corporation which was usually held with no competition
    - Neuse Manufacturing Company (ca. 1923-1927). Involved a tax appeal. (Box 50)
    - Neuseoco Club, Inc. (ca. 1922-1930) (Box 50)
    - News and Observer (1916; 1925) (Box 50)
    - Newspapers (mainly 1925) Assorted letters discussing issues (Box 50)
    - North Carolina State Government (1923-1924) (Box 50)
    - Overman, Lee Slater (ca. 1925). (Box 50)
      This file consists of an exchange of legal advice between Overman and Bailey about the Owensby Case (the subject of a Senate committee investigation) and in relation to the confirmation of Harlan F. Stone as Associate Justice of the Supreme Court
    - Pineland School (1925) Concerns B. N. Duke's generous contributions. (Box 50)
    - Poole, D. L. (1929). (Box 50)
      Relates to an attempt to sue N. C. State University when a student was shot by a security guard who was responsible for preventing trespassing in an orchard adjacent to campus.
    - Poteat, William Louis (1915-1916, 1923, 1926). Personal and financial affairs. (Box 50)
    - Pou, Annie W. Estate. (Box 50)
    - Pou, Mattie. (Box 50)
    - Powelson, W. V. N. Concerns water, hydroelectric, and steam power development in N. C. (Box 51)
    - Pritchard v. Bailey (1931). Election contest. (Box 51)
    - Railroad Freight Rates (ca. 1924). (Box 51)
    - Raleigh Baseball Club (1926-1927). Incorporation. (Box 51)
    - Raleigh Township School Committee v. County Board of Education (1911, 1915, 1918). Disputes over funds and other matters. (Box 51)
    - Raleigh Water (ca. 1926). Concerns a city contract with an engineer. (Box 51)
    - Rand McNally and Company (ca. 1921-1922).school texts for N. C. (Box 51)
    - Red Cross Campaign (1917) Wake County Red Cross War fund (Box 51)
    - Reynolds Contest (1931). Concerns a contest sponsored by R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Co. and the wrapping of Camel cigarettes in cellophane. Members of Bailey's family entered the contest. (Box 51)
    - Rivenbark, Mrs. W. B. (1925). Estate. (Box 51)
    - Saint Mary's Arbitration (1929) Conflict with the city of Raleigh about a street. (Box 51)
    - Sayre, C. Gadsden v. School Committee (ca. 1926). Pertains to a contract dispute. Sayre was an architect (Box 51)
    - Scholarships and Prizes (1924-1925) (Box 51)
    - Schools (1915-1916). (Box 51)
    - Simmons, Furnifold McLendel (ca. 1910-1912). Printed material about campaigns and viewpoints. (Box 51)
    - State Fair (1923). Concerns mortgage on fairgrounds. (Box 51)
    - State Statutes--Prohibition (ca. 1921). Efforts to make N. C. laws compatible with Federal ones. Also reports on Federal liquor agents activities in N. C. (Box 51)
    - State Printing (1923). Concerns a state printing contract and related affairs considered by the N. C. General Assembly; an investigation of the conduct and management of the Office of Labor and Printing. (Box 52)
    - State Theatre, Inc. (1924, 1929). Tax Reform Club Taxation (ca. 1920-1925). Revaluation Act; Revenue Act of 1924; review of Internal Revenue laws of U. S concerning corporations. (Box 52)
    - Teer Nello L. v. George A. Fuller Co. (1928-1929). Concern building the Duke University campus; construction contracts. (Box 52)
    - Thompson Publishing Company (1921). Deals with royalties on a high school textbook, Our Republic. (Box 52)
    - Tobacco Growers Cooperative Association (1927). Concerns an injunction to prevent breach of contract. (Box 52)
    - U. S. v. N. J. Aboud (1926) Case involving fraudulent use of mails. (Box 52)
    - U. S. v. Mrs. Corey (1926). Fraud case, related to Aboud case above. (Box 53)
    - Various other cases against individuals, 1925-1927. (Box 53)
    - Varina (1927). Incorporation of this town. (Box 53)
    - Varner, H. B. (ca. 1923-1924) Another copyright infringement case involving the use of music in theaters. (Box 53)
    - Vinson, Turner (1928). Estate. (Box 53)
    - Vinson estate (continued). (Box 54)
    - Wadsworth, George L. v. Johnson & Johnson Company (1919) (Box 54)
    - Wake County Bar Association (Box 54)
    - Wake County Savings Bank (1920-1931). (Box 54)
    - Waller, John R (1929, 1931). Mortgage bonds. (Box 54)
    - War Finance Corporation (ca. 1922). (Box 54)
    - Watson, N. A. (ca. 1923). A shooting case. (Box 54)
    - Watts, George W. (ca. 1922-1923) Estate. (Box 54)
    - Whittaker, Joel D. A Civil War claim for property taken by Union soldiers. (Box 54)
    - Wills (Box 54)
    - Yellow Cab Company (ca. 1925) Dispute over color trademark. (Box 54)
    - Young, Allen L. (1925). (Box 54)
    - Zebulon Hosiery Mills (ca. 1917) (Box 54)
- Pre-Senatorial Series, ca. 1898-1930, 47 boxes
  - General Subseries (Box 55-57)
    This category includes Items on topics not included in the Subject Files listed below and Items dealing with more than one topic. It includes correspondence between Bailey and Walter Clark, April-May, 1922, on taxes and the governor's race in 1924; speech by Bailey at Pittsboro (April 30, 1923) with reference to the Ku Klux Klan; correspondence with F. M. Simmons, O. Max Gardner, and other state leaders; letters to and from Bailey's friends; and miscellaneous Items.
  - Subject Files Suberies
    - Agriculture (1899; 1915-1930), 7 folders (Box 58)
      Conditions of farmers, mainly in North Carolina; cooperative marketing of cotton and tobacco; tenant farming; taxation of farm lands; crops and prices; and tariffs protecting agricultural products. (See also Taxation; Taxation: Revaluation; War Finance Corporation; Elections: Gubernatorial, 1924; Farmers' Union; and General).
    - Democratic Party, United States; and National Political Concerns (1908-1930)(1 folder) (Box 58)
    - Economic Concerns (1917-1931)(1 folder) (Box 58)
      Banking, economic conditions, economic distress in eastern North Carolina.
    - Education (ca. 1900-1924)(1 folder) (Box 58)
    - Education (1925-1930)(4 folders) (Box 59)
      Public and private-education in North Carolina; Bailey's relationship with UNC-Chapel Hill and his views on public education during the 1924 gubernatorial campaign, textbooks; speech by Bailey on Athletics and the Public (Jan. 30, 1925), comments concerning a speech by Bailey on the ideals of a Christian college; correspondence with G. W. Paschal of Wake Forest College (Sept.-Nov., 1929) on the rise of public education in North Carolina; material on the McLean Bill, the Equalization fund and taxation for an eight-month term in 1929. (See also Taxation; letter of Oct. 20, 1929 in Pre-Senatorial General, from Bailey to O. D. Coffin on his and Biblical Recorder's opposition to University of North Carolina).
    - Election Reform (1921-1929) (1 folder) (Box 59)
      Ballot reform, Australian ballot, primary laws and the need for election reform. In letter of August 26, 1926, Bailey criticizes Blease of South Carolina. (See also Elections: Presidential, 1928--Aftermath; Extravagance).
    - Elections Gubernatorial, 1924. Bailey's candidacy in 1924 Democratic gubernatorial primary against Angus McLean. (Box 59)
    - Elections: Gubernatorial, 1924, Preliminaries (Box 59)
      Correspondence concerning whether Bailey should run, his platform, Watts and the machine in North Carolina politics, the issues at stake, and the prison scandal May, 1923?.
    - Preliminaries, 1921, Jan.-1923, May; (4 folders) (Box 59)
    - Preliminaries, 1923, June-Dec. (Box 60)
    - Elections: Gubernatorial, 1924, Campaign (Box 61)
      Subjects discussed in correspondence and speeches include taxation, agricultural conditions, freight rates, the political machine, law enforcement, and the Ku Klux Klan. There are lists of voters, sometimes with information on occupations or political positions; correspondence with newspapers; and information on newspaper advertising rates (May and June, 1924). Most of Bailey's speaking engagements are documented in Pre-Senatorial Series--Invitations and Engagements. (See also Agriculture; Farmers' Union; General; Labor; Railroads and Ports: Taxation; Taxation: Revaluation; and War Finance Corporation).
      - Campaign (1924, Jan. - Feb.) (Box 61)
      - Campaign (1924, Feb. - Mar.) (Box 62)
      - Campaign (1924, Mar. - Apr.) (Box 63)
      - Campaign (1924, Apr.) (Box 64)
      - Campaign (1924, Apr. - May) (Box 65)
      - Campaign (1924, May) (Box 66)
      - Campaign (1924, May - June) (Box 67)
      - Campaign (1924, June - Dec; 1924, n. d.) (Box 68)
      - Campaign, Form Letters (Box 68)
      - Campaign, Speeches and Published Statements Lists (Box 68)
      - Campaign, Lists (Box 68)
      - Campaign, Lists (Box 69)
      - Campaign, Lists (Box 70)
    - Elections: Gubernatorial 1923, Aftermath (1924, June - 1927, Jan.); (2 folders) (Box 70)
      Reflections on the results of the primary and on the political situation in North Carolina. Letters of interest include those from Bailey to John E. White (July 9, 1914); to Santford Martin (July 5, 1924); and to M. L. Kesler (July 16, 1924). See also the letter from Bailey to H. T. Alexander (July 5, 1924) in Farmers' Union file.
    - Elections: Presidential, 1928. (Box 71)
      Alfred E. Smith's candidacy for Democratic presidential nomination and for presidency on Democratic ticket. Many references to Prohibition, the 1st Amendment, the Ku Klux Klan, and anti-Catholicism.
    - Elections: Presidential, 1928, Preliminaries (1926, Dec.-1928, Mar.) See also letter of Bailey to W. A. Hildebrand (Oct. 11, 1926) in Pre-Senatorial: General. (Box 71)
    - Elections: Presidential, 1928, Campaign
      Includes correspondence for July, 1928, concerning selection of North Carolina Democratic national committeemen and correspondence with, among others, the following - individuals: George Gordon Battle, R. H. Edmonds; O. Max Gardner; O. M. Mull; Joseph M. Proskauer; John J. Raskob; Franklin Delano Roosevelt; C. L. Shuping; John H. Small; Alfred E. Smith; and George R. Van Namee. (See also Elections: Senatorial, 1930, Campaign, for lists of 1928 Democratic state convention delegates; and Racial and Religious Prejudices).
      - Campaign (1928, Apr. - June) (Box 71)
      - Campaign (1928, June - Oct.) (Box 72)
      - Campaign (1928 Nov.; 1928) (Box 73)
    - Elections: Presidential, 1928, Aftermath (1925, Nov. - 1929, Jan.) (Box 73)
      Includes correspondence concerning reorganization of the Democratic Party in North Carolina, particularly F. M. Simmons's role in party affairs and legislation on primaries and voter registration.
    - Elections: Senatorial, 1930. (Box 73)
      Bailey's candidacy against Furnifold McLendel Simmons; for the Democratic senator's -nomination and against George Pritchard for the U. S. Senate seat.
    - Elections: Senatorial, 1930, Preliminaries (1927-1929) (Box 73)
      The decision to run against Simmons. Correspondence with, among others, Broughton, Morrison, Poe, and Robert R, Reynolds. See also letter from Bailey to O. J. Coffin (Oct, 20, 1929) in Pre-Senatorial: General, and material on reorganization of Democratic Party in Elections: Presidential, 1928 (Aftermath).
    - Preliminaries (1927-1929) (Box 74)
    - Elections: Senatorial, 1930. Campaign
      The subject and county folders listed below were apparently created by Bailey's staff during the campaign and have been preserved. The relatively small number of unsorted Items have been arranged by date at the beginning of the category. Most of this material concerns the campaign against Simmons in the Democratic primary rather than against Pritchard in the general election. Material pertaining to the latter race is divided between this category and the one following it, Elections: Senatorial, 1930, Aftermath.
      - Campaign (Box 75)
        - 1930 (Box 75)
        - Bailey Publicity (Box 75)
        - Buttons (Box 75)
        - Clippings (Box 75)
        - Corey, A. (Box 75)
        - Counties, Alamance - Wilkes (Box 76-87)
        - Counties, Wilson - Yancey (Box 88)
        - Expenses (Box 88)
        - Lists--Delegates to 1928 State Democratic Convention (Box 88)
        - Lists--county lists of registrars and judges (Box 88)
        - Prohibition (Box 89)
        - Recipients of Buttons or Folders (Box 89)
        - Simmons Organization (Box 89)
        - Simmons Publicly (Box 89)
    - Elections: Senatorial, 1930, Campaign Speaking engagements (Box 89)
      - Campaign:
        - Speeches (Box 89)
        - Women's Advisory Committee (Box 90)
        - Women's Pamphlet (Box 90)
    - Elections: Senatorial, 1930, Aftermath
      Congratulatory letters and reflections on primary results are interspersed with Items related to the campaign against Pritchard and various miscellaneous topics from 1930. The organization of Items in this category follows the apparent arrangement in Bailey's office.
      - Aftermath:
        - Correspondents, A - C (Box 90)
        - Correspondents, D - C (Box 91)
        - Correspondents, P - Z (Box 92)
        - Election Dispute (Box 93)
        - General (Box 93)
        - The Nye Committee (Box 94)
    - Extravagance (1923-1929) (Box 94)
      A filing category apparently used in Bailey's office files for material related to his 1925 campaign against extravagant expenditures of the state government but expanded now to cover similar material from other years. Some Items concern the prison system and George Pou. There are references to the Highway Commission and other departments of state government as well as to election reform. (See also letter of Bailey to O. Max Gardner, Oct. 18, 1929, in Pre-Senatorial General).
    - Farmers' Union (1920-1928; n.d ). Farmers' Educational and Co-Operative Union of America. (Box 94)
      Correspondence of Bailey with R. W. H. Stone and other material related to the Farmers' Union and Bailey's connection with it. Many references to taxation, agricultural conditions, the War Finance Corporation, and Bailey' candidacy for the 1924 Democratic gubernatorial nomination. (See also Agriculture; Taxation; and Taxation: Revaluation).
    - Internal Revenue Service (1915-1924; n. d.) (Box 95)
      Material related to Bailey's service as Collector of Internal Revenue.
    - Invitations and Engagements (1923-1929) (Box 95)
      Invitations for political speeches, commencement addresses, and miscellaneous occasions, mainly from the period of the 1924 gubernatorial primary. Similar material for 1928 is included also in Elections: Presidential, 1928.
    - Labor (1921-1929) (Box 95)
      Mostly correspondence with the Rev. Tom P. Jimison, Methodist minister and chaplain for the North Carolina State Federation of Labor, concerning Bailey's 1924 gubernatorial campaign and the interests of workers. Also includes material related to organized labor; references to tenant farming; letters of Bailey to Cameron Morrison (Apr. 89 1922), Josephus Daniels (Apr. 15, 1922), and others; a pamphlet on, and other references to, workmen's compensation legislation; and correspondence between O. Max Gardner and Bailey (Oct. 1929 on strikes at Marion and Gastonia.
    - North Carolina General Assembly (Box 95)
      Correspondence of Bailey and members of the General Assembly on various subjects. Reflects Bailey's role in N. C. politics. Bills on insurance, gratuities and other miscellaneous matters. See also N. C. Politics
    - North Carolina Politics (1898- ca. 1925) (Box 96-99)
      Material related to political activity, mainly Democratic, in North Carolina, Much early material (ca. 1910-1918) concerns Raleigh; information in 1913 on commission plan of government for Raleigh and in 1918 on death rate in Raleigh, Items from 1922 relate to Tax Commissioner Watts, taxation, the 1924 gubernatorial election, and the candidacy of Miss Lewis for county treasurer and W. F. Evans for solicitor against John W. Hinsdale. Letter (Nov 17, 1925) from O. Max Gardner about his political plans. Material from 1912 and 1913 includes endorsements of Bailey as candidate for D1 strict Attorney in eastern North Carolina and items related to Simmons' candidacy for the U. S. Senate.
    - Racial and Religious Prejudices (Box 99)
      Items concerning white supremacy, anti-Catholicism, the Ku Klux Klan, and related topics. See also Education; General Elections: Presidential 1928; and N.C. Politics
    - Racial and Religious Prejudices (continued) (Box 100)
    - Railroads and Ports (Box 100)
      Much of this material deals with freight rates and the need for a coastal port in N. C. to facilitate east-west railways in the state as opposed to north-south railways in order to lower rates and aid farmers. Also included are Items dealing with other railroad matters. See also Elections: Gubernatorial 1924.
    - Recommendations and Appointments (Box 100)
      Correspondence concerning recommendations for positions in the highway department, service academies, North Carolina Railroad, postal service, judiciary, etc.
    - Roads (Box 101)
      Material on public roads in North Carolina. See also Taxation.
    - Taxation (1902-1931) (Box 101)
      Material related to U. S. income tax, especially 1920; government bonds; and taxation in N. C. Many Items on N. C. taxes on land. Other Items concern taxation for roads and, particularly in 1929, for schools. See also Agriculture; Education; Elections Gubernatorial, 1924; Farmers' Union; General; North Carolina Politics; and Taxation: Revaluation.
    - Taxation (continued) (Box 101)
    - Taxation: Revaluation (Box 101)
      Material related to the valuation of land for taxation purposes in N. C. and the controversy over revaluation in the early 1920s. See also Agriculture; Elections: Gubernatorial, 1924; and Taxation.
    - Temperance (Box 101)
      Concerns temperance movement, Anti-Saloon League, Prohibition, and repeal of the 18th Amendment. Correspondents include Methodist Bishop Edwin D. Mouzon July 1929. See also Elections: Presidential, 1928.
    - War Finance Corporation (Box 101)
      Concerns the role of War Finance Corporation in providing credit for N. C. farmers, its alleged failure to do so, and the consequent charges during the 1924 Democratic senatorial primary against Angus W. McLean, who had been an official of the Corporation. See also Agriculture; Elections: Gubernatorial, 1924; Farmers' Union; and General.
    - Woman Suffrage (Box 102)
      Material related to the role of women in politics. See also Elections: Gubernatorial, 1924 (Lists: folder of special lists for Suffrage Mailing List.)
- Senatorial Series, 1930-1946, 436 boxes
  - General Correspondence Subseries, 1930-1946
    The papers in this section, largely correspondence plus some printed material, are of a diverse nature and quality. of primary importance is Bailey's correspondence with persons other than family members, such as friends and fellow Senators. Letters not easily placed in subject areas--those discussing Bailey's philosophy of life, history, or the general condition of the world, for example - and letters relating to more than one subject were placed in this section. Information on racial issues is also found here. Correspondents include major state and national figures, newspaper editors, and religious figures. There is a considerable quantity of routine correspondence and some personal correspondence of Bailey's secretaries, especially A. Hand James. The material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - General, 1930, Nov.-1931, Nov. 18 (Box 103)
    - General, 1931, Nov. 19-1932, May 6 (Box 104)
    - General, 1932, May 7-1932, Oct. 30 (Box 105)
    - General, 1932, Nov-1933, July 13 (Box 106)
    - General, 1933, July 14-1934, April 24 (Box 107)
    - General, 1934, April 25-1934, Dec. 25 (Box 108)
    - General, 1934, Dec. 26-1935, Oct. 2 (Box 109)
    - General, 1935, Oct. 3-1936, July 31 (Box 110)
    - General, 1936, Aug.-1937, April 30 (Box 111)
    - General, 1937, May-1937, Aug.-23 (Box 112)
    - General, 1937, Aug. 24-1937, Dec. 31, undated (Box 113)
    - General, 1938, Jan.-1938, April 11 (Box 114)
    - General, 1938, April 12-1938, Aug. 31 (Box 115)
    - General, 1938, Sept. 1-1938, Dec. 19 (Box 116)
    - General, 1938, Dec. 20-1939, June 19 (Box 117)
    - General, 1939, June 20-1940, April 22 (Box 118)
    - General, 1940, May 1-1941, Jan. 31 (Box 119)
    - General, 1941, Feb. 1-1941, Aug. 5 (Box 120)
    - General, 1941, Aug. 6-1942, Feb. 5 (Box 121)
    - General, 1942, Feb. 6-1942, July 20 (Box 122)
    - General, 1942, July 21-1942, Feb. 16 (Box 123)
    - General, 1943, Feb. 17-1943, Oct. 31 (Box 124;)
    - General, 1943, Nov.-1944, Dec. 15 (Box 125)
    - General, 1944, Dec. 16-1946, Feb. 25 (Box 126)
    - General, 1946, Feb. 26-Dec., undated (3 folders) (Box 127)
  - Agricultural Correspondence Subseries, 1930-1946
    Correspondence, telegrams, notes, speeches, statements, and printed material pertain to farming and agricultural products as well as to agencies and concerns of the Department of Agriculture. Of particular importance is material relating to the production and marketing of cotton and tobacco, including such topics as grading, surpluses, voluntary versus compulsory crop control, taxes, ceiling prices, arid specific hills. There is also information on other crops, such as soybeans, peanuts, sweet potatoes, and strawberries, as well as on the poultry, baking and dairy industries. The Agricultural Adjustment Act (AAA) in its various forms and stages, is thoroughly discussed by Bailey and his constituents. Also included are materials relating to the Resettlement Administration, the Commodity Credit Corporation, the Federal Land Bank, the Farm Security Administration. Information pertaining to forestry and the Bureau of Public Roads is found in this section.